[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio my guest is the CTO and co-founder
at ground cover which provides full
stack observability for kubernetes he
was previously the chief Arch at the
healthcare security company cyber MDX
and spent eight years in the cyber
security division of the Israeli Prime
Minister's office he holds degrees in
electrical engineering physics and
biomedical engineering first I'd like to
ask you to pronounce your name and if
there's anything you'd like to add to
your bio hey so it's rovic but you can
call me chz it will be easier yeah
mainly worked around linox embedded
software and distributed systems in the
last 10 years of great this episode is
going to be at the intersection of three
Technologies observability ebpf and
kubernetes I'm not going to go into too
much depth on either one of these so I'm
going to list three episodes here that
covered it in more detail episode 455
Jamie ryel on software Telemetry episode
446 Nigel pton on kubernetes
fundamentals and episode 445 Thomas
graph on ebpf let let's start with
observability jez what is observability
so it's common to think about
observability in three pillars of data
one is the is logging the text messages
we are creating from our applications
the other one is metrics which are
basically counters and gauges that our
application are creating you can think
about that as the speed of a car right
that's a gauge right the fuel amount of
fuel you left in your car and the third
one is tracing which are samples of data
that represent interactions between two
services so if you're calling an HTP
request that will be a trace or a span
which is part of a trace and
observability is the ability to query
all those three in a very meaningful way
of troubleshoot or understanding the
state of application it could be for
security it could be for uh performance
investigations basically everything that
developers are interest on from my
experience observability can make a huge
difference to sort of the quality of
life of the developer trying to get to
the bottom of some problem can you give
an example of a system that didn't have
good observability that was a struggle
to work with and contrast that with
something that had sort of full
observability and how that accelerated
the debugging or the
investigation oh yeah actually I have a
good example of the I think that was the
trigger for me to start ground cover so
we had a a problem with our our platform
where customers experience datal loss
and we had uh some complex pipeline of
data so you know 30 microservices all
talking to each other with message cues
and ready and API calls and everything
you can think of from a modern
application and so you know where do you
start right we got this lead that our
customers saying you know we're missing
data but where do you start at that time
we had a lot of logs but we paid a lot
for them but you know you can't really
read for you know 20 or 30 million logs
line and understand what's going on so
we've decided to instrument our
application with a lot of counters that
will represent the pipeline of the the
system so we took us somewhere around
two months to instrument we had
somewhere around 1 million counters and
then we can finally detected where the
leakage is and start solving it but this
process was a nightmare right so we walk
two months just to get just to see where
the problem is on the other hand you
know when we started ground cover we
knew that we had to set as an example to
How You observe and monitor production
so we we built our entire stack from day
one to have performance monitors and
meaningful logs and traces that will
help us troubleshoot and investigate any
performance issue so you know it feels
like the difference is like you know
using a paper as a map or a a navigation
app that's the difference for me you
know something guid and not you know you
you don't need to search for just see
answers yeah it's a major difference
let's move on to
ebpf ebpf is a technology that's used
perhaps for many different purposes
we're going to talk about observability
but let's just talk a little bit about
the technology at first so what is ebpf
ebpf is technology as you said that
allow you to dynamically change and
adapt the the Linux kernel so a lot of
people can you know first thing they can
say a lot of people that work with Linux
can say okay that's was easy before you
know you just you could write a kernel
module to extend the kernel but the
reality is that writing a kernel model
to extend the kernel it's a very
complicated task and also it could be
very harmful if you if you make a
mistake ebpf is a is a technology that
allow you to extend the kenel with a
very safe way safe in two important
aspects one is from performance aspect
so the ebpf engine that run your program
guarantee that you program are running
very efficiently and they cannot harm
the application itself and the second
one is you're running in a readon mode
of course there are different ebpf
programs and I'm not sure we we should
get into that but in terms of
observability you can run programs with
read only mode that can guarantee by the
kernel to not change the state of the
application it does two allow you to
develop your modules very efficient and
very fast so some people say ebpf is to
the kernel like JavaScript is for the
browser do you feel that's a good
analogy or how would you phrase that
yeah I've heard that many times before I
think it's a great analogy because when
you write JavaScript you don't really
worry about are you going to run on a
Intel machine or it's going to be Mac or
it's a you know the amount of resources
you're going to have you're running in a
sandbox and you get guaranteed by the
browser that your code going to run and
I think that's the magic of ebpf you can
run your program without being worried
about affecting the Linux itself or the
hardware itself and this is something
very very powerful in terms of speed of
development because developing for
kernel today is almost slow as
developing Hardware so I do really agree
with the with this analogy with
JavaScript which basically speed up web
development so I think that's for the
kernel yeah definitely so that's
interesting Which languages can you
write ebpf and are you saying that
whatever language you use it compiles
down to a bite code that works on any
architecture or do you have to compile
it again for x86 and arm and and I guess
which languages do you prefer to use for
ebpf so as you said ebpf is a bite code
itself so that's the running it's the
that's the VM running your instructions
and translated to the proper
instructions set so you don't need to
worry about running on X x86 or you know
that's the kernel will translated and
it's really I know some people write in
different languages high level languages
that compil to ebpf but I think the
majority of software is written in in C
because that will be the the easiest way
to write an ebpf program and don't get
me wrong it's a hard process learning
how to code C code that can translate
into ebpf it's because the verifier the
ebpi verifier is is very picky in
choosing what programs you should run so
you kind of need to learn how to walk
with the compiler to verify your
programs and where that are there
they're safe to run and very efficient
so most people write in C that which
translate into ebpf bite code and run
with this VM with obstruction of the
hardware itself so how about the ebpf
verifier does that run when you compile
the code does that run when it's loaded
into the kernel and can you give an
example where you did have to kind of
fight with the verifier you know what
did you have to do to your code to
appease the verifier or to to make it
load your code so the verier runs when
you try to load the program and also it
depends on the konel version because
when kernel get more sophisticated with
ebpf the verifier get smarter and
smarter and allow you to do more
sophisticated things because again the
purpose of the verify is to make sure
your program is safe so in terms of
things we had to do you you don't want
to know it's a hustle it could be a
hustle even sometimes you know copying
data from A to B and make sure you you
don't have out of bounds copy you really
need to work in terms of making the
verifier happy some people at ground
cover call it you know to know how to
dance with the verifier there are a lot
of examples and every ebpf programmer
probably you know has these kind of
stories every day it's a great
technology but it's still in order to
make it safe and to make sure you know
you can process so much data in a safe
manner the verifier is is picky you need
to know how to please it so a big part
of ebpf are Hooks and I read about you
can hook system calls function entry and
exit kernel Trace points Network events
can you give kind of just an overview of
the different types of hooks and
indicate maybe a little bit what they're
used for there are two major hooks that
you can use and they're separated by the
space they are so if you want to trace
Kel functions you you'll use krops and
if you need some kind of user space
information you'll use yous so why would
you care so KRS are a lot cheaper
because you're already running in kenel
space so you don't need to worry about
contact switch and interrupting your
application so you'll probably want if
your information that you're after can
be retrieved from kenel you probably
want to do that and there are a lot of
books about that we I think Brandon Greg
wrote a lot about that but sometimes
your information could not be retrieved
from kobs I'll give you an a simple
example imagine you want to trace
SSL data the SSL for most run times user
space encryption and you have to get the
information from uprs so you'll use URS
for the libssl lib so of course it will
cost you a little bit more because it's
a user space application and now you can
of have to interupt but it's the only
way to get it so you need to use it
wisely how about Network events I think
ebpf originally stood for extended
Berkeley packet filter although I read
on the ebpf homepage they're trying to
kind of drop that acronym and just call
it ebpf itself but I imagine Network
events are still a primary domain for
ebpf I read about dropping packets it
wasn't immediately obvious to me why
you'd want to drop packets at the EF
level can you give an example of
filtering which I guess is the original
use yeah sure so imagine you're writing
a firewall and you want to do it high
speed and you want to enforce policies
for instance you cannot access an
external IP to this subnet so ebpf can
do that for specific programs so you can
load specific programs that can also
drop buckets so I think the majority of
this use case probably security and high
throughput processing we at ground cover
we do not use these kind of programs
because we don't want to change flow of
information the opposite actually we're
trying to get to extract as much
information as we can without
interfering and to guarantee that so
that's the common use case of dropping
buckets you can also use in the last I
think releases you can also do uh
signaling from the kernel that's also
really powerful from security
perspective you can see signal the
process and even you know sending
termination signals to processes if if
they're doing something wrong so I think
security is a major use case for this
kind of programs I'm sure Thomas with
the episode probably talk a lot about
that and celum project that uses all
those kind of programs so to be clear
with the U probes even if you're in a
readon mode that is a lot of access in
the sense you can look at the memory of
any running user process that's pretty
alien to me as a application developer I
just don't think about being able to
look inside processes but that's true so
I guess you really want to make sure no
one has loaded a ebpf program that you
don't know about yeah so you need to
give right permissions in order to load
ebpf programs you need to have specific
capabilities from the Linux perspective
probably need an elevated user or a
privilege container if you're running on
a kubernetes environment so yes
definitely you know it's amazing
technology when you get a lot of
information you need to use it wisely so
you need to make sure when you're
running these kind of programs you need
to make sure you understand what they're
doing and who's using it and and why so
maybe just two more about ebpf and then
we'll move on to kubernetes and then on
to observability with kubernetes and
ground cover so there are ebpf helper
functions and there's EB e PF Maps I'm
just wondering do those two relate and
particularly how do ebpf maps work it
sounds again unusual to an application
developer so just it'd be interesting to
hear about that so in order to write
programs right we need to have some kind
of data structures we actually pretty
used to them as application Developers
for instance list or or an array or map
those are kind of data structures that
we all familiar and and love and need in
order to use our application and so
those are the same for ebpf because evpa
verifier need to make sure we do not
access arbitrary memory the data
structures that ebpf programs need are
created by the Kel so you work with
functions that are giving you the
equivalent opportunity the equivalent
features of data structures that you
have on your application so map array
TTL or lru cache all of those data
structures are exist in the ebpf
ecosystem and we need them in order to
write efficient and meaningful
applications so I guess one of the
things the verifier is probably doing is
limiting the amount of CPU time that an
ebpf program can have and you're talking
about limiting memory access to what are
those limits are they in milliseconds or
how does that get measured
so it's a configurable but now I I think
milliseconds are out of the the healthy
zones when you write uh ebpf programs
we're usually talking about hundreds of
nanocs that would be a a good direction
and it's also changes with the kernel
version itself so the community is
trying to increase the complexity of uh
evf programs because of the demand so a
lot of products are trying to push down
some of their application into ebpf so
they're also trying to increase the
complexity and the instructions that
ebpf program can run but it will be
around microsc not milliseconds wow
that's interesting let's move on to
kubernetes kubernetes is a huge topic
and we are only going to touch on a few
elements to sort of set the scene for
the rest of the episode but let's start
with what is kubernetes so that's a good
question because a lot of people
describe it differently so some will
tell you it's an orchestration for
containers and some and and me I
personally think it's more than that
it's it's a modern operating systems
because you have all the you know
storage Network scheduling all The
Primitives that we used to know from you
know other operating systems but it's
very native to containers and to Cloud
so to me it's a cloud native operating
system that allow you to run and
orchestrate containers and manage the
resources that each needs I like the
term Cloud native operating system when
I first moved into Cloud development I
did feel that all of the individual
systems reflected operating system
Primitives that we had on a single
machine and so I think that's a good way
to think about it how about the
relationship between kubernetes and
microservices if you're using kubernetes
does that imply you're using
microservices or is kubernetes broader
than that not necessarily but but if
you're using kubernetes using
microservices will become much easier
because microservices require some kind
of orchestration so for instance Network
you need to be able to reach each and
every microservice need to find the
resources that needs from others
kubernetes will take care of that what
do you do when you upgrade how do you
upgrade what are your upgrade strategy
kubernetes have Primitives for that to
maintain the relationship between
microservices so you don't have to write
to use microservices when you're using
kubernetes but it will be easier and
kubernetes will probably be a pretty
good decision if you are heavily using
microservices so I think a big part of
kubernetes is deployment in the sense of
running the containers or systems that
you want in the configuration that you
want is that true that it's mostly about
deployment or once your application or
your back end is up and running what
role does kubernetes play sort of moment
to moment so to me the promise of
kubernetes is the reconciliation Loop so
as developers we know that things can go
wrong something can shut down some
machines will break some storage will be
corrupted and one of the fundamentals of
kubernetes is the reconciliation Loop so
basically what it means is we have the
actual State and desired State and what
kubernetes promised you is to do
everything he can to bring the current
state to the desired state so if process
crashed because you know someone I don't
know Network outage kubernetes will
detect that and recreate it and make
sure it's healthy on another node or
another network and to me that's what's
so great with kubernetes it doesn't
really say you know bad things won't
happen to your production it's all about
making it high availability it's more
like things going to happen but we are
going to do everything we can in order
to fulfill the promise that you ask for
us so in kubernetes there's sort of
hierarchy between these elements
containers pods nodes and clusters can
you talk about these and mention which
of these does the ebpf program operate
on and just sort of how these different
levels relate to observability clusters
are an abstract word of you know group
of Resources Group of nodes if you want
nodes are the machines so that's the you
know the physical representation of all
your compute so we're taking nodes and
now we need to schedule War clades so
deployment or replica sets or wherever
you're you're using with kubernetes
ecosystem so now kubernetes the control
plane has those resources the nodes and
and the desired state which will
manifest with 10 podes that will hold
you know two containers each and it will
start to allocate resources so the
containers will run on those nodes and
if one node will crash it will transfer
it to another and when you scale up your
cluster more nodes will be spinning up
and more pods will scale up so when you
monitor these kind of environments you
want to separate between those two
planes one is the you know
infrastructure so we want to make sure
all of the nodes are healthy not over
booked with high memory or high CPU
usage the network is fine and a lot of
those things can be easily achieved by
ebpf right we just talked about ebpf is
being part of the Kel so each node has
its own Kel and therefore the ebpf
program will cover that and on top of
those you'll have the application itself
so so even if our infrastructure is fine
and your application is you know
returning some broken apis serving
broken API to customers that's also not
a good thing but it's important to
separate between those two planes
because usually it's different people
responsible for those different planes
you have the platform team or the infra
team or or you know whoever responsible
for the infrastructure and you have the
R&D or the the team that actually create
the application that responsible for
those so it's really important to have
the ability to separate between those
two and actually when you think about it
ebpf is also helping with that because
on each and every event you can
correlate it to who is responsible for
it so you can detect if it's a pod
that's triggering this API or it's a
node is it a kernel thing or is a user
space thing so you want to have both and
you want to be able to separate that in
order to find the right people to help
with this
I'm going to ask about kubernetes events
in a little bit but first Docker seems
like the most predominant container
system but I read that kubernetes is not
necessarily bound to using Docker can
you say from your experience what
container systems you have seen and do
they play a challenge for
observability yeah there are a lot of
new Orchestra conization environments uh
I can't really keep up but at the end of
the day kubernetes it's not about how do
you containerize it it's about using
containers so from the kubernetes
perspective it's like a plug and play
right if kubernetes we talked before
about scheduling podes right So
eventually it's running a container
which has an image or manifest and make
it schedule in the Linux ecosystem and
from there it's the containerized layer
to how it will resolve in in Linux
Primitives so From kuet perspective it
doesn't really matter what containerized
platform do you use I did see that
kubernetes allows you to plug in
different systems depending on your
needs it sounds very configurable how
about networking I think networking is a
big aspect of kubernetes I imagine
there's communication going on between
pods but then also between nodes and
then also with the outside world can you
talk just a little bit about kubernetes
if I'm setting up say a new system what
are the different network paths that I
might care about you have a few
objectives that you want to achieve with
networking in kubernetes first you want
to being able to discover your other
microservices and remember that
kubernetes is a flexible system so one
service can hold a 100 PES behind it for
this moment and tomorrow it's going to
have 400 so you need to keep track on
those IPS how can you reach the
microservice that you you're after and
this process can be really expensive in
terms of compute and finding the right
IPS and and maintain it so ebpf is
obviously one of the solutions for that
and and is a great project that try
to push down all these translations and
and rewrite rewiring of packets to ebpf
to do it very optimized that's one
challenge with kubernetes the other one
is how do you expose some services to
the external world so you want to wire
it with Cloud providers you want to you
know to connect it to nlbs or albs and
you wanted everything to be natively and
to be as kubernetes as you can even
though it's interacting with actually
cloud provider which are opinionated so
that's another thing that cloud
providers are doing they're using the
pluggable system ecosystem to join
resources between kubernetes to the
cloud so you can provision an Ingress
controller that will eventually wire to
AWS NLB or the equivalent of of gcp or
or Azure and it will walk out of the box
with a kubernetes native way so that's a
pretty big one because in the past you
had to rewire your application in a in a
proprietary way but today because
kubernetes is becoming the facto
standard cloud provider is doing it for
you and making it kubernetes as native
as possible let's talk about APM in the
context of kubernetes so I think that's
application performance monitoring can
you give us a little overview of that
APM is a general name that represent you
know taking all the three pieces of
observability and tired together to make
some meaningful insights from it
specifically APM is some like related to
traces specifically because this pillar
is is a bit more hard to get right
because you need to either instrument
your application which takes could take
a lot of time or use some kind of ebpf
sensor which just recently became
available so APM is a is General name
for Gathering traces and tie them with
metrics and logs when you say traces I
think of a stack Trace which is a single
program function calling function
calling function is that what you mean
or is there sort of a broader type of
Trace that would involve multiple
programs it's the extension of that so
you're right stra it used to be you know
the way the chain of of events that
happens you know a equal to b equal to C
but then we started using microservices
so now A and B are no longer using the
same process so it's really hard to get
a stack trace for a few microservices
talking to each other so each and every
call is called a span and the chain of
spans are called the trace which trace
this business unit from A to Z and can
investigate it to see where the
bottleneck is where do you get error
from and everything you need to in order
to investigate this incident so I guess
the key with APM is that there are
applications and user applications or or
backend applications as opposed to the
system itself when you think of
observability with kubernetes how does
that divide in terms of what
technologies are focused on the system
versus the applications or is it
basically the same technology so we do
have those two planes we talked about
earlier about you know the
infrastructure plane which are agnostic
to the applications are running on top
of it so you want to make sure the
infrastructure is healthy you have
enough resources in order to fulfill all
the requests that you get as you know to
deploy those kind of microservices to
doing an update and so on so this is one
plane that you want to to Monitor and
obviously if that's broken everything
else going to be broken but still like
if that's healthy and and you know all
the nodes are healthy that doesn't mean
that your application is running
smoothly there could be a network errors
between application there could be you
know wrong configuration different
passwords could be a lot of things so
the other plane is the application
itself and that's harder to monitor
because in order to do that you need
either instrument each and every
application and and not all of them you
wrote the code and there are parties
that you're not aware of and so on and
so that's really hard or you can use
ebpf as a sensor which basically
automatically detect all those traces
and all those spans and and applications
and and get all these data automatically
regardless if you instrumented the
application how about the term service
level objectives is that basically the
amount of uptime that your services have
or could there be other objectives yeah
so each and every platform will Define
what is their slos so what do you
promise to your endusers or customers
what are the standards that you are
achieving when serving their
applications usually we tend to see a
latency promise so you know P95 of all
request will be under 200 milliseconds
for instance that's a very common
metrics and of course I think the golden
signal will be error rate so
what will be the error rate that we can
guarantee to you as an an user or
customer that our platform will provide
and those to measure those that's not an
easy task like it sounds simple but in
order to measure those kind of signals
and you know in order to do that without
you know being involved in each and
every process you either need to use
some kind of ebpf sensors or you need to
have a dedicated team that will make
sure that everything is implemented all
the metrics are instrumented and check
that there no drift because sometimes we
think we're done and then a new
developer add a new API and we forgot
about that so now it's not just we broke
our SLO we don't even know that so
that's not a nice situation to be in you
mentioned
P95 can you explain what that is and why
you use metrics like that as opposed to
say average which maybe is a simpler way
to put it yeah so P95 is a unit of how
do we measure distribution so this will
be the latency that
95% of our application of our apis will
be less than this latency and why it's
important and we're seeing actually a
phenomena where companies are focusing
around P99 or
p999 because it really depend on your
slos so think if you are a bank and if
you have you a P99 of 100 milliseconds
but then you have this anomaly that
takes 30 seconds one out of a million
you won't notice it on the average right
it wouldn't change the average at all
because it's one out of a million but it
could break a trade for a timeout so
those numbers could be very crucial it
depends on your industry and your
specific needs but we're seeing more and
more especially in the gaming industry
especially in the ad Tech and fintech
that those anomalies those one out of a
thousand are matters and for those you
need to measure P99 and P95 and not only
average that makes sense that there's
going to be a few
exceptional events that are much slower
than the rest how about kubernetes
events we mentioned that early on can
you give specific examples of a
kubernets are these related at all to
ebpf hook books or events or is it just
a different topic it's a different type
of events kubernetes trying to
expose some of its state in order to
help us developers troubleshoot so it
generates events normal events warning
events just to give you a clue of what
it's doing and where the problems are so
those are actually really important
because you can find events such as
image pull back off for instance so it
means kubernetes trying to fetch this
container image and can't can't find it
that will probably indicate on a serious
problem it could also have events such
as crash Lo back so it means your
container crashing and you probably need
to check what's going on so those events
could be meaningful but they could also
create a lot of noise it's really
important to know that kuet generates a
lot of events all the time because
that's how it works so it could be
really important but you really need to
understand and digest and dissect what
are the key events that you want to
track you mentioned pulling an image I
did read about deployment changes such
as images config dependencies and I
didn't really think about that in the
domain of observability but I imagine
with
microservices if you have a large system
there could be many different
dependencies and which ones were running
when something bad happened is
non-trivial to figure out can you say a
little bit more about that how are we
tracking what is actually running at a
specific point in time you're definitely
right and especially when those days
compan is trying to push more and more
version each day so it used to be one
version a week so you could basically
estimate what was it at that time but
today we're seeing companies pushing
releases like 10 times a day maybe 20
times a day so
what we do at ground cover because we
generate all those data we tag it with
those specific labels each and every
information each and every trace or log
or metric you want to tag with the right
container image or hash in order to make
the troubleshoot and investigation much
more meaningful because in that way you
can see oh those broken API started with
this commit it wasn't before and I can
see it because it's all tag so it's
really important to achieve that you can
obviously do that with adding labels to
your instrumentation so you can add a
little bit of anotations on your
deployments or your code so it's really
important to maintain that in order to
get a clear sense of what was the
version what was the exact state of the
code at that level how about the
kubernetes API itself is this giving us
information about all of these different
things or is the API specific to
the cluster or just how does that work
those are to me are the most important
things because if you're control plane
if you're you know the infrastructure
doesn't really work if you're node
getting errors from the control plane
the kubernetes control plane that's
really bad and that's could be a sign
that the system is going down completely
so there are those apis which are really
hard to get because they're not
instrumented the cubet is not
instrumented so it's really hard to
detect you can detected with logs if you
are monitoring your control plane logs
and you can do it with metrics if you
are gathering metrics from the control
plane which I advise to do that because
those are pretty important so are you
talking about ebpf ability to see these
kubernetes events it raises the question
does kubernetes is it aware of ebpf at
all is there any sort of synergy between
the two or when you're writing ebpf are
you forced to kind of figure all that
out yourself so when you write ebpf
program you need to sort the kubernetes
relationship by yourself you're using
Linux Primitives like name spaces and c
groups in order to actually get to the
exact container exact po exact
deployment and it's really interesting
and challenging work but it's a must if
you want to translate the kernel layer
into application layer and the ebpf I
think what's great about it is see the
data from the control plane as it was
from an application because at the C
Level it's just an API so when you
translate it to kubernetes layer you can
actually detect oh this API is from the
cuet so it must be a lot more important
than others so you can do that but you
have to navigate through kubernetes
layers in order to find out which Port
is responsible for this API you said
cubet that's the utility I guess you
used to interact with kubernetes or what
was that phrase so cubet is the process
responsible for managing the node so
each node in the cluster has cuet on it
which is responsible for scheduling
containers reporting the status from the
deployments back to you know the control
plane that's the kubernetes unit inside
the node one more question and then
we'll just get into ground cover itself
talking about that in detail Prometheus
and grafana
seem to play a role in observability I
don't think it's specific to kubernetes
but can you just kind of say what those
two are and maybe say what their role is
relative to ground cover also if they
are still used or not yeah so peritus is
the time series it's a lot of things
actually it's a Time series database
it's a format to transfer metrics
between endpoints and it's also a query
language so I think it's one of the
biggest building blocks of time serious
databases PR Meuse so it's also an open
source and also grafana so grafana is an
open source that built I think
originally around metrics and
specifically pritus and it's a
visualization tool so you can visualize
metrics fetch from pritus in grafana and
doing it with you know all the
visualizations that we know like trend
lines and bar charts and pie charts and
gauges in order to make sense from all
those metrics nowadays Prometheus has
competitors like Victoria metric which I
think it's the Next Generation time Ser
database but it's still holds the same
protocol and query language like
promethus so you can still use promethus
Query language to fetch from other time
series database because they're all
implementing the same protocol so it's
very common to see promeo deployments in
kubernetes because a lot of the metrics
are stored there and it's the first
thing to do when you deploy a kubernetes
cluster and you don't exactly have a
plan of how you want to monitor that so
let's get more into ground cover and we
can come back to Prometheus and grafana
and the relationship to ground cover
sort of daily usage so at the beginning
of the episode you mentioned some of
your motivation for starting ground
cover can you get a little more into the
story of how it was started how did you
get your initial customers what
technology did you have at the beginning
did you start with ebpf just kind of
give us a sense of how things got ramped
up so we started with a problem it was
right after the story I had I spent with
the team two or three months
implementing all those metrics and all
those traces and establishing dashboards
and you know I was really proud of the
team it was really hard work and it
worked really well and then the CTO came
and said that the vendor that we used
the usage the observability cost cost
was increased by five times so he asked
for us to remove all those metrics and
all the traces and for me it was a I
felt like it was a failure for me as a
Chief Architect that I could not
understand the cost of observability and
at that time I was trying to understand
is it me or is there something broken in
the ecosystem and from there we kind of
so met shakar and I are good friends and
we sat together and he had similar
experiences so we felt like okay maybe
we're on to something and we talked to
more and more VPR ands and chief
Architects and and we saw this as a
common problem so we saw there are two
major problems one is companies don't
have enough information and they're
working really hard to get more and more
information spending time on that and
not deploying new features to customers
and the second one is the companies that
do have the information they cannot pay
the price for holding it so they're
actually reducing some the information
in specific environments or you know
they do not deploy it on development
environment and then they miss bugs or
anomalies in their Dev staging
environments and we realize we need to
do something different or to solve it
better and we kind of walk with this
idea for a few months you know wondering
how we can do that in a frictionless way
we realized we have to do observability
in a frictionless way so no friction for
on boarding no friction with payments
and then we encounter ebpf and we
realize okay the first thing is we use
ebpf the onboarding is going to take
five minutes that's done we get a lot of
information even more information we had
in the past but now we actually have a
bigger problem now the amount of data is
actually bigger and we understood that
you have to leverage stream processing
you so you think about stream processing
as pushing down some questions common
question that you want to ask to the
source of the information so you don't
need to ship all this data from A to B
just in order to ask the question you
can just ask the question constantly
when the data is originated and save a
summary of it so that way you can reduce
the volume of data that you need to save
and reduce cost with that so once we
realize those two can be solved we
started ground cover which is the best
friction as observability platform so I
think one of the features of ground
cover is doing the processing in the
nodes maybe instead of sending it back
to a backend at your company is that
different than how other observability
tools work exactly so that's the first
part is the stream processing so instead
of sending all the data to somewhere
else and then querying it we're doing
the processing at the node level and
reducing the cost of sending it
somewhere else if even in ter terms of
eress which means sending data outside
of your cluster that could be really
really disturbing to have this kind of
you know sending all those data we're
talking about terabytes a day that's the
volume we're talking about in modern
companies could be very very expensive
but you touched on another point which I
think is something fundamental with the
observability word is vendors trying to
convince you to send as much data as
they can they charge by volume so they
want you to send as much data you can
and on the other hand the customer wants
to save money so they want to send as
less possible there so you have this
Paradox between the vendor trying to
send as much possible the customer
trying to you know filter as much
possible and we realized modern
observability vendors should be on the
same page with the customer so that's
why we decided early on that we're not
going to charge by volume so it makes us
on the same page it's kind of alignment
between us and the customer that we do
not encourage you to send data that you
don't need and we are on the same page
with you that you're going to have all
the data you need and not data you don't
need we're on the same page and I think
it's important to be aligned with your
customers needs when talking about ebpf
we said it has very tight time limits as
to how much process it can do I'm
guessing this stream processing cannot
run inside of ebpf so are we saying ebpf
collects the data and then you have a
different process running on each node
that filters the data or monitors the
data I guess yeah that's correct that's
the trade-off between what to do in line
inside ebpf programs and you know how
much can we push the boundary of doing
everything we can in the ebpf because it
will be much more efficient and how much
we offer flow to do it out of bound and
in other process that will take this
information and I think we are
constantly trying to understand where
are the boundaries for that we are doing
a lot inside ebpf to make sure we are
sending only data we need in order to
reduce the total computation cost and
the big important thing to remember is
the expensive part is to send data from
the node itself because that will
involve serialization deserialization
Network between availability zones and
so on and that will be expensive so as
long as you can push down filters as low
as you can to ebpf there and on top of
that do the outof bound stream
processing and not interfering the
application I think that's the way to go
and that's the way to make it
frictionless as possible in terms of
affecting the application so if I'm
using ground cover I could imagine three
situations one I'm using stock ebpf
programs from you or you're installing
them for me two is I'm using your ebpf
monitoring but I've configured it in
some way I've told it what to to look
for and three I don't know if this ever
happens but as a customer I actually
write my own ebpf I'm just wondering in
ground cover which of those is most
common or which is possible the first
and second options are pretty common we
see customers you know trying to just to
make it so we're trying to we have this
number 5 minutes in ground covers that
it should be running under 5 minutes no
matter the cluster size so we're doing
everything we can to make it as fast as
we can no unnecessary questions just
works but obviously more advanced users
can configure the evf programs and
tracing so if you don't want to capture
you know ready protocol for instance
some customers are not interested in
that some customers are really
interested in that so it's opinionated
we will allow you to write filters in
order to you know drop some namespaces
some workloads some protocols that will
be a more advanced usage of crown cover
we still do not support ad hoc ebpf
programs and to be honest I did not get
any requests for that because I think
most people don't really want to write
ebpf programs they just want to that it
works but it could be interesting idea
to make it dynamically so maybe add
dynamically ebpf programs on demand so
definitely something to think about you
mentioned the five minutes setup period
I guess for trial what's actually going
on there how is the ebpf program loaded
on all of my nodes if I have a lot of
nodes running what's Distributing the
actual program to those nodes so we we
it's not a try because our first cluster
is fre forever so what we do is we use
demon set primitive which basically
tells kubernetes that you want to run
this pod on each and every node so we
kind of ask humanties to take the
responsibility of managing it for us
because what we want is to have our own
ebpf programs running on each node so we
use demon set for the sensor and from
there we guarantee that each and every
note has this ebpf program running and
loaded into the canel you're saying
demon set is that a kubernetes API or is
that something yeah so that's a
primitive from kubernetes primitive that
making sure that you get a copy of this
application on each and every node the
usage for that will be Monitoring
Solutions Security Solutions maybe
infrastructure so imagine you want a DNS
server on each and every node or you
want a cni plug-in or any network
related or storage related drivers on
each and every note it's like the demons
in on our old operating systems
right something that's always running so
maybe touching back to promethus and
grafana what sort of dashboard and
visualization features are inside of
ground cover and in what cases do I
still pipe the data to one of these open
source platforms so we decided really
early that we really love grafana we do
not want to build custom dashboard we
focus around the ebpf and the databases
behind it and the data model and the
performance of that and so we do not
want to build another dashboarding
system so we made a architectural
decision to use pritus as our quiring
language from the beginning so you can
basically get your grafana and Route it
to our platform and fetch all the data
from our platform as it was your pritus
we also host grafana as part of our
solution so in order to also eliminate
that friction if if you don't want to so
we also have all the common you know
visualizations as hit maps and trend
lines and bar stacked bars and pie
charts all the regular thing because
once we decided to use promethus as the
query language we could reuse a lot of
components that already know how to work
with that I think that makes a lot of
sense how about this is a little behind
the scenes but you're using C or like a
c like language to write the ebpf what
other languages are used at ground cover
say to implement the stream processing
what languages do you use we are using
goang as our major programming language
we had a long discussion between goang
and rust and decided to go with goang
because of the ecosystem we also took a
lot of inspiration from projects like
victoriia metric which took go Lang to
another another level of performance and
memory management so which I a lot of
Concepts also from them so yeah goang
and and c and behind the scene we're
using Victoria metrix as the database
for metric and click house for logs and
traces and events both are amazing
Technologies really inspiring piece of
technology and we're trying to squeeze
it to the max for our use cases can you
say a bit more about Victoria metrics I
hadn't run across that one yeah Victor
metric Is An Open Source Time series
database I think it's somewhere around
like five years old definitely winning
on every Benchmark we did and they have
a lot of uh white papers and Benchmark
they did it's like the next level for me
of Time series database they took pritus
concept and brought it to a new era a
new level of implementation so I
definitely encourage everyone to check
it out especially if you're using
promeets today or using tanos I think
that will be probably pretty easy drop
in replacement and save you a lot of
time and and money speaking of Open
Source how about ground cover itself I
know the whole project is not open
source but there are may be some open-
Source components that you guys have
been developing yeah we're trying to
contribute to open source wherever we
can we released more which is a CLI tool
for kubernetes CPU and memory monitoring
we also released ketta which is an ebpf
sensor that demonstrate some of the
abilities of what you can do with ebpf
so that could be also a good starting
point for people or Engineers want to
play with kubernetes and ebpf
specifically it's pretty cool project
you can get a lot of meaningful
information from it a lot of network
metrics from it so we are contributing
to open source wherever we can I think
the world of software is pushed by open
source and we're trying to pay our part
wherever we can going back to go for a
second I think kubernetes itself is
written in go is that true yeah the core
of it yeah the kubet of itself yeah how
about this case study you had on your
blog you guys have a pretty extensive
blog I found it interesting to read
through there was a company or a project
called common ground and I know they
used go on AWS but python for machine
learning on gcp which is a split that
I've seen myself where you use both
Cloud providers what observability
challenges were there with this sort of
dual Cloud setup so I think whenever you
have different deployments on different
even regions or even products for
instance kubernetes and serverless or so
even that will be really challenging to
get a a full picture of your production
posture so obviously having two Cloud
providers will be not an easy task to
monitor what I believe is that you
probably want to have a monitoring
cluster so dedicated cluster for
Monitoring Solutions
and then configure all the other
clusters and all the other clouds to
send data to this cluster in that way
you guarantee that this cluster will
remain available even if you have some
kind of disruption and you also get a
full picture agnostic to the cloud
itself that is running so you want to
push all the data to one place you
probably want to use some kind of
standard formats like Auto or Prometheus
remote right or other Open Standards to
consolidate the data and then you need a
strong back observability back end that
will be also coste efficient in order to
hold these data and retain it to the
attention you need I had kind of forgot
about serverless in this conversation
that does seem like it presents a
challenge so kubernetes seems to mostly
deal with long running containers but I
imagine a specific system might have
long running containers but also use
serverless maybe specifically Lambda I
guess in that case you're going to
observe it when it makes that call or
how do you even know that it's made a
call to a function like that so when
you're using ebpf sensors you only need
one side of the conversations instead of
having the two sides when you're using
traditional instrumentation so as long
as your lambda's at the end you know
talking to something orchestrating
kubernetes you're fine but there are
cases when your the entire stack is is l
for instance and when you have this
situation you kind of need to instrument
your application anyway so specifically
in ground cover that's why we have these
end points that can allow you to ingest
data from external sources so if you're
using any open standard you know zipin
or Jagger or open Telemetry of course
you can just ingest external data and we
make sure to treat it as a first class
citizen the platform itself so I guess
going back to that 5 minute setup
process what do I get at the end of
those 5 minutes what turns on what do I
start seeing is it the data flowing into
my grafana instance or how do I know
I've succeeded in the setup process
after you deploy ground cover you'll go
to the platform itself the app.
cover.com and you immediately see all
your workloads with all their golden
signals monitored by the platform so you
don't need to do anything in order to do
that it will be automatically created
with your account and your email or the
registration API key from there you can
explore we have the I think pretty cool
map view so you can visualize all your
production workload in a map and that's
pretty impressive to see you know what
you created in a map view and you all of
a sudden detect some kind of weird
things that you never thought you'll see
you see that some third parties
applications are actually reporting some
things to some vendors and it's really
interesting to see see and of course
from there you can also integrate with
other third parties so you can integrate
with oal in gesture you can integrate
with your grafana you can integrate with
our alerts and slack and to set up as
your primary solution for observability
two things there and then we'll start
wrapping up you mentioned golden signals
I have down here latency traffic errors
and saturation I'm not sure what
saturation means but are those the
signals or does it just mean like
whatever signals are important to you
so I think golden signals traditionally
yes it's those signals you have the
equivalent of that it's called the red
signals it's the same thing without the
saturation which is a bit more complex
topic but yeah those are the signals the
golden signals which according to a lot
of sres those are the signals that you
want to start monitor when you have no
idea what is important to you so does
saturation relate to CPU usage or is it
a networking thing so it could be it
depends on what resource your
application is actually consuming so
saturation will say will tell you how
much of the resources that you require
are you maxing out so if you're maxing
out your resources you're soon getting
your limit so if your limit is bounded
by CPU or by Network or by disk that
will affect your saturation rate and
then one final clarification you
mentioned getting a map of your system
that's not an ebpf map that's like a
visual boxes and lines type of maper
yeah sure map could be a award that is
representing different stuff in this
stock but yeah I'm talking about a
visual map that will guide you where
data is Flowing inside your system and
and outside honestly great let's start
wrapping up I think when this episode
airs we'll be looking forward to
2024 so it might be a little bit far
ahead but what do you see as the future
of ebpf in the industry and at ground
cover what are you going to do in 2024
or looking forward to doing in the
future I think ebpf will eventually be
on each and every server that we use so
if you have a production platform that
running servers you're probably going to
run ebpf programs for a lot of tasks
because we're just started seeing what
we can do with ebpf in terms of security
in terms of performance in terms of
observability so ebpf is definitely the
future and we we just start seeing it
and all the vendors in the security or
observability domains are going to
leverage it and it's that's exciting for
me because we are constantly working on
pushing ebpf boundaries as far as we can
so I think 2024 as we all know is also
going to be interesting in terms of AI
and how do we make sense from
observability data with AI as you know
the volume data is getting crazy and
with that it's getting really hard to
make sense of it so there is this
promise of AI getting us guided with
that how can people learn more about
ground cover or follow you online so you
can follow me on LinkedIn or Twitter
also we're writing a lot of blogs all
the engineering are really interested in
writing blogs technical blogs in ground
cover so you can go to to the website
and go to blog and you feel free to send
me a message regarding ebpa for
observability great I'll put links to
those in the show notes thanks for
joining me today chz this has been
interesting thanks for having me it's
really cool this has been Philip Winston
for software engineering radio thanks
for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at
[Music]
sr.ntr or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]